Pick up today, today's דף daf is ס"ה samekh hey sixty-five. We
pick up at the last line of ס"ד עמוד ב'. samekh dalet
amud bet. We're in the middle of a whole discussion, I mean
the גמרא Gemara actually interesting sort of like reminded itself of some
previous discussions it hadn't gotten to from the last, you know, פרק
perek about can a נכרי nokhri be מבטל mivattel עבודה זרה, avodah
zarah, you know, if he himself does not worship עבודה זרה. avodah
zarah. First it said you could be מבטל mivattel עבודה זרה avodah
zarah of a god that you don't worship. If you're a Zeus
follower, you can be מבטל mivattel the עבודה זרה avodah zarah of
Aphrodite's or whatever. But how about if you're a non-idolater altogether? And
that was like an issue. And then it, but that led to
a discussion about this whole question of who is the considered to
be a בן נח? ben noakh? Who is considered to be a,
excuse me, גר תושב? ger toshav? And is it just not being
עובד עבודה זרה? oved avodah zarah. Is it accepting the שבע מצוות
בני נח? sheva mitzvot bnei noakh? Either of which are to some
degree relatively low standards considering what the תורה Torah expects in general
of non-Jews, or a very, very high standard that basically he has
to observe all the מצוות mitzvot with the exception of נבלה, nevelah,
which is imagine there's some position in between anyway. So and
so one of, so in general for questions about relevance for, what
relevance does what הלכה halakhah does it matter whether you're a גר
תושב? ger toshav? So, so a standard one is as we are
going to sort of see in a minute is whether there's a
מצווה להחיותו, mitzvah le-hayoto, a positive obligation of care. But the other
relevant question is, right, to what degree, I mean for our, to
live in Israel, I'd imagine, right?
Well right, the immediate issue in the תורה Torah whatever is that
you dwell in the land of Israel and so on and that's
part of the obligation of care. Somebody that has like a right
to be living in the land of Israel was an obligation of
the people of Israel because the גמרא Gemara is not mentioning exile
communities, so that means if you're living in your land then it's
כגר כאזרח. ka-ger ka-ezrakh. It exactly is intertwined with that. But you're
right to point that out. And the immediate relevance for this מסכת
masekhet is the question about whether they make סתם יינם stam yeinam
by touching it.
And we'll see a related issue in a minute, you know, and
that as we mentioned the other day that תוספות Tosafot actually speaks
about there Christians that are not עובדי עבודה זרה, ovdei avodah zarah,
whatever תוספות Tosafot thought about Christianity, but and or maybe minimally they
just don't even use the wine in their עבודה זרה avodah zarah?
practices. Again maybe outside the actual act of what do you call
it, communion. Not communion, is that what it's called? Communion? Well yeah.
And transubstantiation. Anyway, all right fine. Anyway, so תוספות Tosafot at a
certain point says, oh, so the wine wouldn't be אסור בהנאה assur
be-hana'ah because it's not עבודה זרה avodah zarah related, but it's still
אסור בשתייה assur be-shtiah because there's still an issue of בנותיהם. benotayhem.
Which is actually what the גמרא Gemara said at the end of
yesterday. Their wine is like their oil. It's a very powerful comparison
because their oil, okay fine they changed the גזירה gezeirah about their
oil. But their oil, their bread, their food, all of that was
about issues of intermarriage. They wasn't about issues of עבודה זרה. avodah
zarah And therefore to say what is when a somebody is in
the גר תושב ger toshav category, there still is intermarriage concern, so
it's like all those other intermarriage foods and therefore you can't drink
it, okay, or eat it, whatever, but it's out of the עבודה
זרה avodah zarah. category and you can get הנאה. hana'ah. So while
the גמרא Gemara yesterday made that only for somebody who's in this
formal category of a גר תושב, ger toshav, as we pointed out
you know there's a whole approach in תוספות Tosafot to make that
a general category, a category for even somebody who just the technical
concerns of יין נסך yayin nesekh and עבודה זרה avodah zarah didn't
apply. Like if they say that Christians didn't use it in their
worship, that would also lead, you know one major thrust in תוספות
Tosafot was that would lead to a similar issue. That you can't
drink it because of intermarriage, but it's not אסור בהנאה. assur be-hana'ah.
But anyway in the גמרא, Gemara, it was about that formal personal
status issue of categorizing someone as a גר תושב. ger toshav. Okay.
So now we pick up with the last line with that in
mind. Like who is a גר תושב? ger toshav? I mean what
how do certain non-Jews that are not עובדי עבודה זרה, ovdei avodah
zarah, how does some of these עבודה זרה avodah zarah הלכות, halakhot,
specifically עבודה זרה, avodah zarah not non-Jew הלכות, halakhot, but עבודה זרה
avodah zarah, הלכות halakhot relate to them and do you have to
formally be in a category of גר תושב ger toshav or just
in practice not be עובד עבודה זרה? oved avodah zarah, Wait, I
want to, so let's just see that because the גמרא Gemara was
up like you know a real punch like you know gets to
it in the very first line of the דף daf today. So
last line of ס"ד עמוד ב'. samekh dalet amud bet. רב יהודה
שדר ליה קרבנא לאבידרנא ביומי
דאידא. Rav Yehuda shaddar lei korbana la-avidrana beyomei de-eida. Rav Yehuda sent
a gift and I think the word is fascinating: קרבנא, korbana, a
קרבן korban as a very religious ritual sacrificial you know kind of
you know sort of meaning you know connotation. Anyway he sent this
gift to Avidrana on his holiday. So you send your doorman a
Christmas gift, okay, on Christmas and how you do this? What about
the whole איסור issur of יומי דאידא, yomei de-eida, the first משנה
mishna in עבודה זרה? avodah zarah Six two two months ago weren't
you there you know weren't you paying attention since the beginning of
the
מסכת? masekhet? I know, he doesn't, yeah, okay, fine, it's—now notice it
says—I know it's Christmas, but I know that he's not so פרום.
frum. I know that he doesn't really worship the gods on this
day. Okay? It's, so therefore, now the funny thing is, so why
do you send him a gift on today? It seems that, so
that's why I use the Christmas example, because it seems like there's
still culturally the idea that on this holiday, on this Zeus day,
Aphrodite's day, St. Patrick's day, I don't know, just the other day.
Anyway,
the practice would be to send gifts, and even though you're doing
it for like the cultural practice, and it would seem like it,
it seems, it wasn't just by chance, oh it was his birthday
today, okay, nevertheless, even though it was part of that whole cultural
practice, it was still allowed because he knew that he in particular
was not participating in the religious dimension of the day. So A,
that's surprising that he allowed him to do it even on the
day itself when everybody else might have been doing it for a
religious context. And number two, it doesn't say he's a גר תושב.
Ger Toshav. He was מקבל שבע מצוות בני נח. mekabel sheva mitzvot
bnei Noach. He was מקבל mekabel all of the תורה Torah except
נבילה. neveilah. As long as למעשה lema'aseh it doesn't apply to him
in particular, that's okay. And that led to תוספות Tosafot at the
very beginning of the מסכת masechet discussing doing business with Christians on
Sundays, etc. How much you judge the particular individuals involved in their
practice and so on, or does it have to be a formal
personal status category? So whereas yesterday the גמרא Gemara spoke about this
status of גר תושב, Ger Toshav,
here it's just talking about the fact that in practice he's not
עובד עבודה זרה. oved avodah zarah There's a question, yes?
Yeah, in terms of categories and concern of רבנו תם Rabbeinu Tam
and all sorts of things, I could see from a Talmudic
perspective doing the same thing for עם הארץ, am ha'aretz, like well,
we don't want our daughters marrying...
All right, but thank God they did it because there was also
the sense to which these types of things creates barriers and sets
and creates lines and says who's one of us and who's not
one of us and so on. So you saw that the rabbis
might have emphasized that you should be נושא בת תלמיד חכם nosei
bat talmid chacham and not נושא עם הארץ, nosei am ha'aretz, etc.
They did not want to use these things to create those types
of lines. It also gets into important questions about attitudes towards קראים
Karaites and so on. How much did they
apply צדוקי—not Tzadoki צדוקי—Samaritans Tzadoki in the time of the גמרא? Gemara?
These things also had a very powerful social message and context about
defining who's one of us and who's not one of us. So
it wasn't just like the technical concern of, oh, ideally you're not
supposed to marry בת תלמיד חכם—that bat talmid chacham there's—בת עם הארץ
bat am ha'aretz whatever. Yeah. Okay, anyway, so now the גמרא Gemara
continues. אמר ליה רב יוסף—so Amar lei Rav Yosef רב יוסף Rav
Yosef said והתניא—so ve-hatanya רב יוסף Rav Yosef challenges this. How do
you make a decision just based on this person's personal practice? Whatever
his status is still as an עובד עבודה זרה, oved avodah zarah;
whatever his personal practice is.
והתניא, Ve-hatanya, איזהו גר תושב? eizehu Ger Toshav? כל שקיבל עליו בפני
ג' חברים שלא לעבוד עבודה זרה. kol she-kibel alav bifnei gimel chaverim
shelo la'avod avodah zarah. Minimally, even if למעשה lema'aseh he doesn't עובד
עבודה זרה oved avodah zarah, and שבע מצוות, sheva mitzvot, there needs
to be some formal act of accepting that status upon oneself. It's
not just in practice he doesn't do it. So the גמרא Gemara
says כי תניא היא להחיותו. ki tanya hi lehachayoto. Yeah, that idea
of a formal גר תושב Ger Toshav status, that's for the מצווה
mitzvah of a positive communal obligation to sustain the person and support
the person and so on. But it's not for these things that
are רבנן, rabanan, עבודה זרה avodah zarah? concerns. Those things we can
judge on a more case-by-case basis. So it's a really, like I
said, it gets really to the heart of it. Not everything requires
a change of personal status. It's enough to know you're not עובד
עבודה זרה; oved avodah zarah for you, I can do business
ביום אידו. be-yom eido. How it applies, but things that are more
like the social communal issues of status, okay, those are things that
actually requires this change of status. Where does wine fall in this,
okay, in the middle of a whole discussion about wine, and we
just discussed yesterday wine was about who constitutes a גר תושב. Ger
Toshav. It seems from the
גמרא, Gemara, until we say otherwise, that wine would require a formal
change of status. It's not enough just in practice. But again, we
discussed תוספות. Tosafot. Now תוספות Tosafot is talking about
an entire religious community. All Christians don't use wine in the following
ways. Okay, so that maybe, that's somewhere between those two. That's the
difference between you as an individual don't do it, and that might
be good for giving you a gift on your holiday, as opposed
to you formally accepted this status, that's what we need if we
want to have a positive obligation
להחיותו, lehachayoto, as opposed to nobody formally accepted a status, but it's
not true at an individual level. It's true at the entire, the
entire religious practitioners aren't עובדי עבודה זרה. ovdei avodah zarah. Right? How
about this issue? Let's talk about Muslims. Okay? What's the story for
Muslims for wine? So רמב"ם Rambam says Muslims are like גירי תושב
geirei toshav since Muslims don't
basically have any form of עבודה זרה. avodah zarah? עבודה זרה avodah
zarah in their religion, they don't even have, totally reject all even
all images and so on. They're like גרי תושב gerei toshav and
there is no problem with being נהנה ne'neh from their wine. You
can't drink it, intermarriage, but there's no problem about being נהנה. ne'neh.
Now, he never says you have a positive מצוה להחיותו mitzvah lehachayoto
they're in the formal גר תושב ger toshav category for other things,
okay, but on the other hand, it's an entire you know group
of religious
practitioners, there maybe we're willing or similar to what תוספות Tosafot did
by Christians for wine, we're willing to reassess their status by wine.
Okay, so you've really got three categories. You've got the person that
all of the people that are from your religious class or whatever,
all the non-Jews in this in this area are pagan, you an
individual are a good, pure monotheist, whatever. Okay, that might have limited
applicability in הלכה, halacha, maybe about the issue about יום אידם yom
eidam or something like that. Then you've got people that formally accept
whatever they need to formally accept to be גר תושב, ger toshav,
that's great for everything, even להחיותו. lehachayoto.
And then you might have people in the middle that don't formally
accept the new status, but as an entire religious people you know
an entire religion aren't עובד oved עבודה זרה, avodah zarah. and that
might you know be one level you know up from the individual
and might even have the status in terms of issues like wine.
So different questions
about individual, an entire group, a formal acceptance of status. And which
הלכות halachot change based on where somebody is situated along that continuum.
You translate להחיותו lehachayoto as like a rescue mission, right? להחיותו lehachayoto
is if he falls into the pit, you have to like bring
him out. That's different than like, oh he's on hard times and
let me you know give him a little.
Yeah, no, no. להחיותו lehachayoto is more proactive. More you know right,
yeah. להחיותו lehachayoto is וחי אחיך עמך. vechai achicha imach.
Didn't we use it before about the pit?
Maybe, but here anyway it's more proactive. It's it's at a higher
מדרגה madreigah than that. It's not just.
How do we see that?
I don't know, but normally that's the context it's read. It's like
וחי אחיך עמך vechai achicha imach type of thing. Okay, so now
the גמרא Gemara says like this. Okay. הכי תניא להחיותו. hachi tanya
lehachayoto. ואמר רבה בר בר חנה אמר רבי יוחנן, ve'amar Rabbah bar
bar Chana amar Rabbi Yochanan, גר תושב
שעברו עליו יב חודש ולא מל הרי הוא כמין שבעובדי כוכבים. ger
toshav she'avru alav yud-bet chodesh velo mal harei hu kemin shebe'ovdei kochavim.
Very harsh statement. Doesn't appear anywhere else, isn't quoted in the הלכתי
halachic literature.
A גר תושב ger toshav who hasn't had a ברית מילה bris
milah within twelve months is as bad as like a non-Jew apostate,
which is a pretty harsh term. Okay, you know, he's a terrible
person. So you know you don't give him any special status, standing.
Just because he didn't do a ברית מילה, bris milah, which is
pretty bizarre, which makes it sound like you expect a גר תושב
ger toshav eventually to convert, right? And if he's not converting, it's
like גר תושב ger toshav is like he's in a conversion class.
It's like a way status between becoming leaving עבודה זרה avodah zarah
and becoming a full Jew. So you expect him it sounds like
that's what he was thinking of a גר תושב, ger toshav, somebody
that you're expecting to convert within a year. And if he hasn't
converted within a year, ach, worthless. Okay, so how do you say
that somebody's a גר תושב ger toshav just you know with these
other things about like not being עובד oved עבודה זרה avodah zarah
and so on? So the גמרא Gemara says no, כגון, kegon, התם
כגון
שקיבל עליו למול ולא מל. hasam kegon shekibel alav lamul velo mal.
That's a case where he said he was going to do a
ברית מילה, bris milah, that it he made it clear that he
was in the process of become presumably of becoming Jewish. So then
like if he doesn't do it within the year that he was
sort of said he was going to do it, you sort of
give up on him. But normally somebody can comfortably inhabit the גר
תושב ger toshav status without us assigning any sense of blame that
you didn't finish it to become a Jew. Okay, alright. So now
the גמרא Gemara says like this. רבא אמטי ליה קורבנא לבר שישך.
Rava amti lei korbana leBar Sheshach. Now that we've spoke about giving
gifts on יום אידם, yom eidam, like this should have been the
discussion we had two you know sixty דף daf ago, okay about
people that even weren't a גר תושב ger toshav just had basically
personally given up עבודה זרה avodah zarah so or not done it
not worshipped עבודה זרה. avodah zarah. So now we're going to have
a starting like that about רבא. Rava. רבא אמטי ליה קורבנא לבר
שישך. Rava amti lei korbana leBar Sheshach. רבא Rava delivered or presented
a not a the word is sacrifice but a gift to בר
שישך Bar Sheshach ביום אידא beyom eida on the pagan holiday.
Does קורבנא korbana ever mean a gift?
Yeah, so I think that's I haven't had a chance to look,
that's a good question.
It says here קורבנא דתשורא. korbana detishura.
Right, which is a gift. Yeah, I understand. So I haven't had
a chance to look.
תקרובת Tikrovet is a gift, isn't it?
No, תקרובת tikrovet is actually is an offering to עבודה זרה. avodah
zarah.
So I haven't had a chance to look if it's used that
way elsewhere in ש"ס, Shas, whether you know but it certainly is
very suggestive to be using it in a context of where it's
permissible to give a gift on יום אידם. yom eidam. So that's
what I said, it's like oh, every presumably everybody else is giving
these gifts in a religious context, it's Christmas everybody's giving well it's
the opposite the difference is that Christmas everybody gives it in a
more secular holiday you know a commercialized holiday context.
Like someone giving chocolate on Easter? Maybe that.
Isn't it just as much a
commercialized
I don't know what.
Alright, whatever it is, anyway but it seems everybody else might be
giving it in a religious context, but But can you say along
with that a Happy Holidays or would you just give them? I
don't know. Okay, לבר שיתא ביומי דאידם *L'bar sheita bi'yomei d'eidam*.
אמר ידענא ביה דלא פלח לעבודת כוכבים *Amar yadana beih d'la palach
l'avodat kochavim*.
I know he personally isn't עובד עבודה זרה avodah zarah *oved avoda
zara*. אז *Az*, so now that's the end of that, that was
the end that tied up just another example with the previous thing
that you don't always need a status of a גר תושב Ger
Toshav. *ger toshav* in order for some of these עבודה זרה *avoda
zara* types of הלכות *halachot*. Now we're going to have a fun
story. אזיל אשכחיה *Azil ashkechei*, so Rava went, I don't know if
it was on יום אידם Yom Eidam. *yom eidam* or some other
day, and he found this בר שיתא דיתיב אצווארי בורדא *Bar Sheishach
dyatib atzvarei bevarda*. He was sitting in a bath full of rose
petals וקיימן זונות ערומות קמיה *v'kaiman zonot arumot kameyh*.
And there were naked prostitutes around him. He had the 70 virgins.
אמר ליה *Amar leyh*, אית לכו כי האי גוונא לעלמא דאתי *it
l'chu ki hai gavna l'alma d'atei*? So this Bar Sheishach said to
Rava: 'Ah, this is עולם הבא *Olam Ha-ba*! Do you have any
reward like this in your עולם הבא *Olam Ha-ba*?' אמר ליה *Amar
leyh*, so he said to him: דידן עדיפא טפי מהאי *Didan adifa
tfei mehai*. Our עולם הבא *Olam Ha-ba*'s better. טפי מהאי *Tfei mehai*?
אמר ליה *Amar leyh*, טפי מהאי מי הוה *tfei mehai mi hava*?
What could be better than this? אמר ליה *Amar leyh*, אתון איכא
לכו אימתא דמלכותא *Atun ika l'chu eimta d'malchuta*.
You might think look at all this good גשמיות *gashmiut* and being
able to indulge all of your lusts, but you live under the...
you're subservient to your king. אנן לא הויא לן אימתא דמלכותא *Anan
lo havya lan eimta d'malchuta*. We won't have to be subservient to
any human being in our עולם הבא *Olam Ha-ba*. We're just directly
with God. Of course the funny thing is why doesn't he saying
this is physical lustful pleasure, it's not the same as the religious,
but maybe this Bar Sheishach couldn't appreciate it. See what's interesting is,
okay, one minute. אמר ליה *Amar leyh*, אנא מי אית
לי אימתא דמלכותא *Ana
mi it li eimta d'malchuta*?
He says: 'I'm so wealthy and I've such status. What does that
mean? I don't live in fear of the king.' עד יתיב *Ad
yatib*,
while they were sitting and talking,
אתא הוא פריסתקא דמלכא *ata hu pristaka d'malka*, a certain messenger from
the king came. אמר ליה *Amar leyh*, קום
קבעי לך מלכא *Kum k'ba'i lach malka*.
Get up, the king needs you. Okay, just to prove Rava's point.
כי נפיק ואזיל *Ki nafik v'azil*, as he was running out of
the house, he said: אמר ליה *Amar leyh*, עינא דבעי למיחזי לכו
בישותא תיפקע *Eina d'ba'i l'michzei l'chu bishuta tipaka*. Ah, you Jews you're
on such a high מדריגה *madrega*, clearly as soon as you say
something God makes it come true. Look this messenger of the king
came. Anybody who looks evilly at you their eye should pop out.
Okay. אמר רבא Rava, *Amar Rava*, אמן *Amen*. So Rava said אמן
*Amen*. And guess what happened? פקע עיניה דבר שיתא *Paka eineih d'Bar
Sheishach*. So his eye popped out. I don't know why he was
looking evilly but whatever. Maybe because he said that with a certain
amount of envy, ugh, you guys you always get it right. Okay,
anyway, אמר רבא *Amar Rava*, okay so, אמן *Amen*. אמר רב פפא
amar Rav Pappa, *Amar Rav Papa*, איבעי ליה למימר ליה מהאי קרא
*Iba'ei leyh l'meimar leyh mehai kra*. Rather than just saying we don't
have the אימתא דמלכותא *eimta d'malchuta*, which doesn't really challenge the assertion
of an idea of עולם הבא *Olam Ha-ba* as being this type
of physical pleasure and lust and so on, he should have rather
quoted the following verse. Again, I don't know with all the naked
prostitutes, but he should have quoted the following verse: בנות מלכים ביקרותיך
*Bnot melachim b'yikoroteicha*,
the daughters of kings will be your honors. The way Rashi reads
it, נצבה שגל לימינך *nitzva shegal liminecha*. Rashi says it means יקר
*yakar*, like your honor. Tosafot gives another read. Anyway, the prostitute or
the favorites, your concubine will stand to your right hand בכתם אופיר
*b'chetem Ofir*, with the gold of Ofir. So maybe, I don't know,
maybe אדרבה *aderaba*, that's not, well, against what I was saying, that
אדרבה *aderaba*, there's exactly a פסוק *pasuk* that exactly sounds like this
about having obviously this very male fantasy also having all of these
beautiful women surrounding you. But here they'd be not זונות *zonot*, they'd
be women of status, they'd be princesses. אמר רב נחמן בר יצחק
*Amar Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak*, איבעי ליה למימר ליה מהכא *Iba'ei leyh
l'meimar leyh mehacha*. שגל *Shegal*, right, I wrote like concubine or whatever.
To me, yeah, because he had תשע
מאה שגלות *tesha mei'a shegalot*. Right, so that's more, that's maybe more
of the זונות *zonot* category. He should have said מהכא *mehacha*, and
this is pointing to again a different type of an עולם הבא
*Olam Ha-ba*: עין לא ראתה אלהים זולתך יעשה למחכה לו *Ayin lo
ra'ata elohim zulatecha ya'aseh l'mechakeh lo*. An eye has not seen, God,
only You, no person, no human being can imagine what the עולם
הבא *Olam Ha-ba* will be. God, this is what You will do
to those who long for You. Okay, so that was the end
of that fascinating little fun little short אגדתא *agadata*. But again, very
relevant in terms of everything we've been learning this entire מסכת Masechet.
*masechet*. When does a non-Jew get out of the category of an
עובד עבודה זרה *oved avoda zara*? And for which הלכות *halachot*? The
high הלכה halacha *halacha* of להחיותו *l'hachayoto* or positive obligation of care,
to get out of the דרבננס *d'rabanans* about יום אידם Yom Eidam.
*yom eidam* etc., or this middle issue about יין נסך yayin nesech,
*yayin nesech* which seems to be more
status based.
What I wanted to say was what's interesting is that the I
think they had this whole story to show that the guy may
not be moral at all in terms of what we consider to
be important, sleeping around or whatever it is. But nevertheless we can
still send him a gift.
I think you are correct. I think the point is that there's
a difference between whether we approve of this person's behavior in general
and... technical concerns about יום אידם. Right, you know, and let's say
you decided that these people were still violent and murderous, so you
might not be able to sell them weapons or other types of
things, or you might not be able like the earlier גמרות Gemaros
that related to ייחוד Yichud and other these types of issues, but
that doesn't mean you can't give them a gift on יום אידם.
Right. And that is exactly what happens when you try to, when
you're not status-based. If you're status-based, you would say you can't have
somebody that's still doing A, B, and C, and call this person
a גר תושב. Ger Toshav, But you might be able to say
I'm not interested in whether they're a גר תושב, I'm interested in
whether I can sell them wine. I'm interested in whether I can
give them a gift on יום אידם. Right. And that exactly could
be more exactly a more like a very, very, you know, narrow-focused
type of a question.
What's the status of Buddhism? Boom.
That is beyond the scope, context of this דף. daf. Okay, שכרו
לעשות עמו מלאכה אחרת. Secharo la’asos imo melacha acheres. So getting finally
back to the משנה. Mishnah. So you're not allowed to earn money
from working with עבודה זרה wine, or יין נסך, yayin nesech even
סתם יינם stam yeinam according to the גמרא. Gemara. What about if
you hired a person to work for you for the day, and
most of the work he was moving your furniture, whatever, he he
was
and then just some time during moving your furniture, you said, oh,
can you go bring those barrels of wine, you know, up from
the basement and bring them to the storehouse? So as long as
the general hire was for general work, in the middle of that
you can do some סתם יינם stam yeinam or יין נסך yayin
nesech. work. That's what the משנה Mishnah claims.
But he shouldn't try to get out of it and say, well,
you know, well,
according not according to the משנה. Mishnah. Let's see what the גמרא
Gemara says. ואף על גב דאמר ליה לטותי ערב. V’af al gav
d’amar lei l’tutei erev. That sounds like even if he asked you
to do this not after it was already like, you know, the
evening time.
ורמינהי. U’remi’nhu. But I'll ask you because we've got a תוספתא Tosefta
that says that that type of a request is only good after
it's five o'clock. You know, the guy says, ah, it's five o'clock,
your day is over, do me a favor, before you leave, could
you please bring over that wine from the basement? That's okay, because
your day is over and you've earned your pay, so now you're
not doing it for pay. But if he, but (What's his pay?
Your nine hours of pay, now you're doing it out of...)
Yeah, that's a good point, but no. שכרו. Secharo. But the issue
is about being paid for it. It's a type of הנאה hana'ah
being paid for it and making money off of it and so
on. Okay, so the תוספתא Tosefta says, השוכר את הפועל, Hasocher es
hapoel, you hired a worker, לטותי ערב, l’tutei erev, towards like when
it's nightfall, אמר לו, amar lo, הבא חבית
של יין נסך ממקום למקום, hevei chavis shel yayin nesech mimakom l’makom,
do you mind bringing up that barrel of wine? Okay, he didn't
exactly call it יין נסך. yayin nesech, שכרו מותר. Secharo mutar. Then
it's permissible. So טעמא דאמר ליה לטותי ערב, Ta’ama d’amar lei l’tutei
erev, it was only because he said it basically at nightfall after
you had done, you'd earned your wages for the day, in.
But the rest of the day you wouldn't be allowed to do
that. אמר אביי הכי קתני נמי מתניתין דאמר ליה לטותי ערב. Amar
Abaye hachi kasni nami masnisin d’amar lei l’tutei erev. Fine, that's the
case of our משנה, Mishnah, which does not פשט pshat at all.
רבא אמר לא קשיא. Rava amar lo kashya. It's not difficult. הא
דאמר ליה העבר לי מאה חבית במאה פרוטות. הא דאמר ליה העבר
לי חבית חבית בפרוטה. Ha d’amar lei ha’aver li me'ah chavis b’me'ah
prutos ha d’amar lei ha’aver li chavis chavis b’pruta. If you say,
look, here'll be your job today to be carrying a hundred barrels
for a hundred dollars, and ninety-nine of those barrels was, were figs,
and one barrel and one barrel was wine. So in that type
of a case, you didn't earn any pay until you did all
hundred barrels. So because, because that one of those barrels of wine
was part of what allowed you to get earn your entire lump
sum payment of a hundred dollars, okay, then it's
then it is all seen as money earned because of work with
יין נסך, yayin nesech, and you basically can't benefit from any of
the pay, which seems a little harsh, but that's ההלכה. ha’halacha. If
however, the person said I got a lot of barrels to move,
I will pay you a dollar per barrel, then, and one of
the barrels you moved is סתם יינם, stam yeinam, okay, then you
can at least keep ninety-nine of the dollars, and you just don't
accept the other dollar. Now of course, the funny thing is that
then that's you know, that then, okay, fine, well then what happens
with לטותי ערב, l’tutei erev, which is what תוספות Tosafos says? So
I don't get it, if the case is, so anyway let's read
that. So hold on, הא דאמר
ליה העבר לי מאה חבית במאה פרוטות Ha d’amar lei ha’aver li
me'ah chavis b’me'ah prutos. הא דאמר ליה העבר לי חבית חבית בפרוטה.
Ha d’amar lei ha’aver li chavis chavis b’pruta. Okay, ותניא נמי הכי,
V’sanya nami hachi, we taught similarly in a ברייתא. Braisa. השוכר את
הפועל ואמר לו העבר לי מאה חבית במאה פרוטות ונמצא חבית של
יין נסך ביניהם, Hasocher es hapoel v’amar lo ha’aver li me'ah chavis
b’me'ah prutos v’nimtza chavis shel yayin nesech beineihem, one of them was
wine, שכרו אסור, secharo asur, so you can't benefit from any of
it. חבית חבית בפרוטה ונמצא חבית של יין נסך ביניהם שכרו מותר.
Chavis chavis b’pruta v’nimtza chavis shel yayin nesech beineihem secharo mutar. However,
if it's you're being paid individually, you can keep the money for
the other stuff. So okay, so the case in the משנה Mishnah
where you can do it in the middle of the day is
when you're being paid individually and then you just won't get the
pay for that one barrel that you're doing of יין נסך, yayin
nesech, you say this I'm doing for free, okay, I'm not getting
paid for that. Okay, the other case where if it's during the
middle of the day you can't get it is when it's a
hundred dollars for the whole thing. So then the question is, but
if it's a hundred dollars for the whole thing and you finished
your hundredth barrel after the evening, what difference does it make? Right?
It's about the whole lump sum being a hundred dollars. It's not
clear how לטותי ערב l’tutei erev helps in that context. So תוספות
Tosafos tries to figure that out, it's not a clean answer, okay,
but at the end of the day, the גמרא Gemara sort of
bracketing the whole לטותי ערב l’tutei erev and limiting the case of
our משנה Mishnah where it works. where you're being paid per piece.
But yes, the right question to ask is, if it's a problem
when it's a lump sum and it's not defined by the hours
you're working, but by the number of barrels, how does it all
of a sudden become okay if you're doing it after hours? Okay,
so that is a good question which תוספות Tosafos tries to figure
out. All right, so now let's continue. השוכר את החמור להביא עליה
יין נסך שכרו אסור. Hasocher es hachamor lehavio aleha yayin nesech secharo
asur. If the guy pays you to rent your donkey
for transporting יין נסך, yayin nesech you can't keep the money, even
though he's not renting your services, it's still payment
for doing, for like, work that's being done with יין נסך yayin
nesech. even though it's not your personal work.
I guess something like that.
תחת ששכרו מותר Tachas shesecharo mutar just to get back to that.
So returning to that משנה, Mishnah, except for that little piece. Yeah,
correct. It doesn't say that.
Correct. הא תו למה לי? Ha tu lamma li? Why do you
need to tell me this in the case of the donkey? היינו
רישא, Hainu reisha, that's the end. I don't know, to me it's
a חידוש. chiddush. It's one thing to say since this remember this
is not a general הלכה Halacha, of איסורי הנאה, issurei hana'ah, specifically
about יין נסך. yayin nesech.
It's one thing to say we don't want you personally working with
יין נסך. yayin nesech, It's another thing to say that the guy's
hiring the donkey, he's using the donkey, you're staying at home, you're
just collecting for the donkey. He could do whatever he wants with
the donkey. Because he happened to inform you that he's using it
to use barrels of wine that makes it forbidden? It's like, to
me, it's like I'm not personally connected. So to me there's definitely
a חידוש chiddush that even though I'm not personally connected, if he
tells me he's using it for wine, it's forbidden, but the גמרא
Gemara wants to go even further.
So this is real יין נסך, yayin nesech. like as opposed to...
Yeah, the גמרא Gemara at the beginning of the פרק perek said
it would be true by סתם יינם, stam yeinam, it doesn't say
explicitly by these cases as well, but yes, the משנה's Mishnah יין
נסך. yayin nesech, Okay. היינו רישא. Hainu reisha. סיפא איצטריכא. Seifa itztricha.
No, no, no, you need the end case. שכרה לישב עליה, Sechara
leishev aleha, the end of the משנה, Mishnah, אף על פי שהניח
עובד כוכבים לגינו עליה שכרו מותר. af al pi she-hinniach oved kochavim
legino aleha secharo mutar. If, however, he said I want to hire
your donkey because I want to ride it, not that I want
to transport יין נסך, yayin nesech. then even if he decides while
riding it that he's going to put his flask of wine on
it, it's permissible. Okay, because then it's not primarily about transporting wine,
it's primarily about transporting himself and the use of it for his
flask of wine is completely incidental. Okay, but the גמרא Gemara exactly
now asks about that. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like this:
למימרא דלגין לאו דינא הוא לאותבי? Lemeimra dilagin lav dina hu le-osvei?
So the גמרא Gemara thinks the only reason it's permissible for him
to put his flask of wine is that he doesn't have a
right to put his flask of wine, that wasn't part of the
rental agreement, and therefore you're not actually being paid for that, because
he only has a right to put his tush on it, not
to put his wine on it. So למימרא דלגין לאו דינא הוא
לאותבי? lemeimra dilagin lav dina hu le-osvei? He doesn't have a right
to put his flask of wine? ורמינהי, Vermina, ask on this: השוכר
את החמור ליום, hasocher es hachamor leyom, if somebody hires out a
donkey for the day, שוכר מניח עליה כסותו ולגינתו ומזונותיו של אותו
הדרך, socher maniach aleha kesuso veliginaso mezonosav shel oso derech, the renter
is allowed to put on it, now there's a question if כסותו
kesuso means his clothes, like his clothes his change of clothes for
the next day, or תוספות Tosafos reads it כסתו, kesto, his כסת,
keses, his pillow. Okay, any which works better. Anyway, and his wine
flask and the food that's going to be if we're traveling for
a week, I get to carry my week's worth of provisions on
the donkey. Okay, של אותו הדרך. shel oso derech. מכאן ואילך, Mikan
ve'eilach, and חמור מעכב עליו, chamor me'akev alav, and if he wants
to put any more burden on the donkey, the donkey driver can
say no, I'm sorry, you don't have the right to do it.
חמור, Chamor, now the donkey driver, this is by the way, now
this might be why just to go back to what I said
before, why the גמרא Gemara thinks it's פשיטא peshita because I said
the example was like I rent you my car and I'm staying
at home, I rent you out my donkey and I'm staying at
home. And to me that's a big חידוש, chiddush, even though I'm
not involved and
you're at... I can't rent you my donkey for you to use
יין נסך. yayin nesech But now we see that actually a standard
way of renting out a donkey is I don't stay home, I'm
renting out, it's like renting out my limousine, I'm also the limousine
driver, I'm also the donkey driver. Now it makes a lot more
sense, the גמרא Gemara says פשיטא. peshita. Okay, so I'm involved in
שלעפינג schlepping your סתם יינם, stam yeinam, right? Okay, now it does
make a lot more sense, which actually leaves open the question: what
if I'm not involved? What if I just rent out my car?
Am I allowed to do that if you're going to use it?
Can I rent... can I be in a U-Haul company and you
come to me and you say, 'Oh great, how much? Fifty dollars
a day? Great, I got all my יין נסך yayin nesech, I
got to move.' I said, 'Wait, wait, I can't rent it to
you?' So I don't know, I think if I'm not involved, it
may be really different. But now we find out that I am
involved. Okay, so you as the guy on it can use it
for your wine flask and for your provisions for the trip. And
what do I get to do?
Okay, is there not a general issue about being משתכר באיסורי הנאה?
mistaker be-issurei hana'ah?
No, that was what we said at the very beginning of the
פרק. perek. חמור, Chamor, מניח עליה שעורים, maniach aleha se'orim, I get
to have use it to carry the bundles of whatever the bags
of, what do you call it, barley ותבן ve-teven and straw, meaning
which is going to be the donkey feed, ומזונותיו של אותו היום,
u-mezonosav shel oso yom, and my own food, we're going to say
in a minute why it's different, I don't get to carry on
the donkey my food for the whole
trip, for
the
week. Exactly, the more weight, the slower things are going to be.
So, anyway, but bottom line is, the question is, ah, but if
the renter's allowed to put his wine flask, then when he rents
it and you’re, it's implicit that he's going to be having his
wine flask, so you're being מסתכר mistaker with יין נסך, yayin nesech.
why is that okay? So אמר אביי, amar Abaye, נהי דלוגין דיניה
הוא לאוזפי, nehi delogin dinei hu l’ozefei,
yes, it's true, he has a right to put his wine flask
there. מי קא אמר ליה, mi ka amar lei, מוסיף לי מי
אמר ליה, mosif li mi amar lei, נכית לי אגרא דלגינתו. nechit
li agra delginato. But if he doesn't put his wine flask, the
renter doesn't get to say, "Oh, I get a ten-dollar deduction per
day because I didn't use it for my wine flask." It's like,
no, you're not paying me for the wine flask, you're paying me
for your personal trip on it. I'm not transporting wine, right? It's
like when I go ahead and take a taxi, I mean, okay,
sometimes I think they charge an extra thing per bag or whatever
that might be different if they actually charge an extra per bag,
and then I'm paying him extra per bag. But like, normally, you
take a taxi, you don't get to come into the taxi and
say, "Oh, I get a two dollars off today because I didn't
bring my bag, you know, I didn't put my bag in the
trunk." Like,
the fee is the fee, if you want to put a bag
in the trunk, be my guest. So therefore you're not being paid
for the bag. And therefore even if he does use the bag,
even if the bag is סתם יינם, stam yeinam, that's not what
the pay is for, or יין נסך. yayin nesech Okay, now the
גמרא, Gemara, so that's a very nice elegant answer. Now, היכי דמי,
heichi dami, what's the case here where the renter gets to have
the week's worth of provisions and the, and the, I'm not the
renter, the whatever, the renter's the guy who's doing the renting, the
traveler gets to do the week's of provision and the donkey owner
only gets to do the day of provision? היכי דמי, heichi dami,
אי דשכיח למזבן, ei d’shchiach l’mizban, so if, you know, you're going
to be stopping at inns and and fairs and whatever markets, and
you're going to be able to buy food along the way, חמור
נמי לעכב, chamor nami l’akev, so the donkey driver should also be
able to say, "Why you can't take a week's worth of provisions?"
ואי דלא שכיח למזבן, v’ei d’lo shchiach l’mizban, and if there's not
going to be opportunity to buy food along the way, סוחר נמי
לא מעכב, socher nami lo meakev, why does
the traveler have a right to prevent the donkey owner from more
than a day? The donkey owner will say, "What do you mean?
There's not going to be provisions along the way, I also need
to eat." So what's the difference, one guy gets for the whole
trip and the other guy gets just for the day? So אמר
רב פפא, לא צריכא דשכיח למיטרח ולמזבן lo tzricha d’shchiach l’mitrach u’l’mizban
מעונה לעונה. me'ona l'ona.
No, you can go to the effort when you're at your, when
you're at your waystops and, you know, and you can hustle around
and get extra food, but it's a pain, you'd rather just, you
know, take all your food with you from the outset, especially people
charge, you know, the prices that they charge at these highway stops.
So חמר דאורחיה למיטרח ולמזבן. chamar d’orchei l’mitrach u’l’mizban. So the
donkey driver, he's supposed to be doing the work, that's why you're
paying him. So let him, when you get to your stop, let
him go spend, you want, you're the guy who's paying for the
donkey, you want to just go to your inn, relax after a
long day, have your meat or whatever, take a sleep, let the
donkey driver worry about feeding the donkey, buying provisions for the next
day, that's his business. סוחר לאו דאורחיה למיטרח ולמזבן. socher lav d’orchei
l’mitrach u’l’mizban. So that's why if, you know, if the customer is
always right, if you're the customer, you have more right to take
more food with you than the actual donkey driver does. Okay. אבוה
דבני רב אחא בריה דרב איקא avuh d’vnei Rav Acha brei d’Rav
Ika הוי, hava,
so now the father, one more story about earning money with wine,
הוה ושדי ליה חמרא לעובדי כוכבים. hava u’shadi lei chamra l’ovdei kochavim.
What he would do is he would pour out wine that non-Jews
would buy. Now the general practice that רש״י Rashi says is, pour
out, wait a minute, I'm pour it into their flask. I don't
mean like pour it out to waste. So Michael here is a
non-Jew coming to buy wine from me. Now the normal practice would
be that he would pay ten dollars a barrel and he'd get
the barrel as part of the deal. Okay? So what, but what
I would do is I would go ahead and I'd take this
barrel and I'd pour it out into the various flasks. Michael wants
all of his flasks filled with wine, he's going to go bring
them to I don't know, to his workers or something like that.
Okay? And he owns the barrel, but now the barrel is empty.
But all the wine that's in the flasks now is because because
Michael owns them now, and there's an interesting question in תוספות, Tosafot,
are they mixed with a little remnant of יין נסך yayin nesech,
that was in the flasks from before, or does it just because
they become in now into his flasks that makes them אסור assur
even though he hasn’t touched them yet? But we’re not going to
worry about that right now. But by going into his flasks it
became forbidden. Okay, and now so that's what he, I filled up
his flasks, he owns the barrel, but the barrel is empty. Okay,
חמרא לעובדי כוכבים chamra l’ovdei kochavim ואזל מעבר להו מעברא. v’azal ma’avar
lehu ma’avra.
And then what I did was I helped him cross the river,
you know, on this type of a, you know, with on a
on a
ferry or something, thank you, you know, and I helped him bring
all these flasks across the river. ויהבי ליה גופיה באגרא v’yahavei lei
gufey b’agra and he let me keep the barrel for my fee.
Okay, now we've got a problem, the problem is... That I seem
to be doing business with יין נסך, yayin nesech I mean, you
know, earning money. So אתו אמרי ליה לאביי, atu amray lay l'Abaye,
they came and they said this to Abaye, how can he do
this? אמר ליה כי קטרח בהתירא קטרח. amar lay kee katrach b'heteira
katrach. No, it's all he's operating with התר. heter. Now what does
it exactly mean that he's that he's operating with התר, heter, right?
I mean when you meaning he was focusing not on crossing the
river but on pouring out the wine. When he poured out the
wine, the wine was still התר. heter. That's all very nice about
pouring out the wine, but then he said one minute, ורוצה בקיומו
דלא נצטרו זיקי, v'rotzeh b'kiyumo d'lo nistaru ziki,
so one minute, but first of all we remember we dealt yesterday
with the problem of this idea of רוצה בקיומו, rotzeh b'kiyumo, which
seemed to be an independent issue like מקיים כלאים, mekayeim kilayim, an
independent issue of earning money is just wanting the stuff to wanting
the יין נסך Yayin Nesech, to remain. So we have three things:
selling the wine, which is okay because the wine is התר; heter;
the wine crossing the ferry, I don't want the wine to spill
because I'm still responsible for it, so that's a רוצה בקיומו rotzeh
b'kiyumo problem; and then being paid for having them cross the ferry,
which is a משתכר mishtaker problem. So pouring the wine is okay,
בהתירא קטרח. b'heteira katrach. But then it says ורוצה בקיומו דלא נצטרו
זיקי, v'rotzeh b'kiyumo d'lo nistaru ziki, so one minute, he doesn't want
the flasks to break because he's responsible for them. No, דמתני בהדייהו,
d'masni b'hadayhu, he explicitly stipulates if the flasks break in the crossing
they're not my responsibility, so I'm not רוצה בקיומו. rotzeh b'kiyumo. אי
נמי דמייתו פריסטקי בהדייהו, ee nami d'maisu pristaki b'hadayhu, or that he,
you know, what do you call it, or he, what do you
call it, oh, or that he brings over other like while I'm
transferring them over on the ferry, I've got other jugs with me,
so if the flasks break, no big deal, I'll just transfer the
wine to the other jugs, which I'm not exactly getting because then
it means okay, I don't really need the flasks to not break
because I could always transfer it even though it'll be a royal
pain in the תחת, tochis, but even if that's true, I still
don't want the wine to spill even if I'm okay with the
flasks breaking because I'll transfer it to jugs, I'm still רוצה בקיומו
rotzeh b'kiyumo of the wine, right? Even if he focuses on the
barrel, right, I know. But if the flasks break, if they break,
the wine will go back in the barrels. I understand that, I
understand that, but I don't understand, I'm still רוצה בקיומו rotzeh b'kiyumo
of the wine, right? But there's no direct connection between the רוצה
בקיומו rotzeh b'kiyumo of the wine and keeping the barrels. I, yeah,
but I don't see the גמרא Gemara yet being about that. כלים
ריקם, keilim reikam, רש"י Rashi does
say it, he doesn't say it's
about the barrels itself
that I'm being allowed to keep. Remember the גמרא Gemara about, maybe,
I'm still not totally getting it, I hear what you're saying.
Anyways, then the גמרא Gemara says הא קא
מעבר להו מעברא,
ha
ka
ma'aver lehu ma'avrah,
but I don't understand, he's actually transferring them over the river and
he's being paid for, he's being משתכר mishtaker with the wine. So
it says דקטרח באיסורא, d'katrach b'issura, and he's doing
effort with, you know, I don't know, it just says טרח, tarach,
I don't know why it doesn't say משתכר, mishtaker, I think it
should have said, but anyway, you know, he's dealing with the wine
and getting paid for it. דאמר ליה למברומי מעיקרא, d'amar lay l'mavrumi
me'ikara, no, he told the, the guy who runs the river, apparently
he wasn't the one on the ferry, he told the ferry ahead
of time, he said, I sell wine to people, you know, here's
a hundred dollars upfront and go ahead and every time my customers
come, have them go over. So, so I don't, I still don't
get it. Like so why isn't the ferry owner being משתכר באיסורי
הנאה? mishtaker b'issurei hana'ah? Because he's not doing business with the buyers,
I'm the one paying him. And so, like, אי נמי דנקיט פוקיטרי,
ee nami d'nakit pukitri, here רש"י Rashi said, because I'm having the
ferryman do it. So, but why isn't the ferryman is presumably getting
paid by me. Well we're not worried about the ferryman right now,
we're just dealing with... Yeah, but what, so the ferryman is being
עובר. over. That's if the ferryman is a Jew. That's interesting, the
ferryman isn't Jewish, maybe. Or it says I gave him פוקיטרי, pukitri,
like a knot, like I basically gave him a pass, like here's
a voucher, I didn't personally transfer them over. So again, I find
this strange, I just in general I find the רוצה בקיומו rotzeh
b'kiyumo question strange. Like when is just my desire for the thing
to exist a problem per se? And you know, maybe the point
is correct somehow if it doesn't directly tie in with the barrels.
But anyway, but also what's interesting and it gets back to my
example of renting a car if I'm not the one driving the
car, that even though they are giving me the barrel presumably for
my involvement in helping them get across the river, since I'm not
personally the one taking them across the river, it's somehow not a
problem of משתכר באיסורי הנאה. mishtaker b'issurei hana'ah. So to me this
is very interesting and
somewhat limiting the problems of משתכר באיסורי הנאה. mishtaker b'issurei hana'ah.
The funny thing is that רש"י, Rashi, תוספות, Tosafot, the רי"ף, Rif,
the רא"ש, Rosh, like nobody talks about it.
And to me, to me it seemed like a very interesting limit
on the problem without a clear articulation of exactly why it's okay,
like you know, but it seems like because somehow
my lack of personal involvement makes it okay.
So it would be the same thing if let's say you own
a moving... Right, so the U-Haul certainly would seem to be yes,
would seem okay from this גמרא, Gemara, but I would have liked
to have had a little more discussion. Anyway, let's go on, next
משנה. Mishna. Now we switch gears to the type of stuff that
we learn when we are learning כשרות Kashrut in יורה דעה. Yoreh
Deah. Okay, so this might be conceptually like the last section of
the, of the מסכת. We dealt with wine, what defines wine. What
about the כיתאי דכיתרי? Kitey de Kitrei? Yeah, I did that. There
are knots, which is basically like a pass. You give somebody some
special knotted rope and it shows them that they're allowed to pass
the ferry, a coupon or whatever. Anyway, so we dealt with what
makes when is the wine wine, what type of touch, doing business
with איסורי הנאה, Issurei Hana'ah, or not business, being hired out. And
now we deal with mixtures. And what type of mixtures are a
problem and these are the types of things that you deal with
when you're learning כשרות. Kashrut. It so annoys me, this is a
brand new building, we always have to deal with the stupid knocking
of the pipes. You think that they know how to create buildings
these days that don't have that problem. Okay, anyway, let's take a
look at the משנה. Mishna. יין נסך שנפל על גבי ענבים. Yayin
nesech she'nafal al gabei anavim. You have this יין נסך, Yayin Nesech,
not even סתם יינם, Stam Yeinam, really יין נסך, Yayin Nesech falls
on top of grapes. So now are the grapes forbidden, did they
absorb the taste? It's all cold. Normally cold isn't a problem. So
ידיחן, yedichan, rinse them off, והן מותרות, vehen mutarot, they're permissible. ואם
היו מבוקעות, ve'im hayu mevuka'ot, if the grapes were cracked, then אסורות,
asurot, then it's forbidden, because even though normally you need heat, there
is realities of absorption. If I have some טריפה treifa נבלה neveila
stew that falls onto even if it's cold נבלה neveila stew that
falls onto my slice of bread and it absorbs, oh it's all
cold, not a problem. It does really absorb, something's absorbed that are
porous. So anyway that would be an issue. אסורות, Asurot, they're forbidden.
נפל על גבי תאנים או על גבי תמרים. Nafal al gabei te'einim
o al gabei temarim. Let's say it fell on figs or on
dates. So then again presumably those would be considered porous. Okay which
is interesting, really are dates porous, like what if it fell on
apples you would rinse it off? I guess dates are a little
more porous than grapes. I don't know. Anyway, so it says, it
sounds like they're porous and it's a problem, but there's still the
following qualification. אם יש בהן בנותן טעם אסור. Im yesh bahen benosein
ta'am assur. If it's enough to give taste, it's forbidden. And here
becomes one of the... What about the מבוקעות? mevuka'ot? You didn't say
anything... Because because יין ביין, yayin be'yayin, so Michael asks a good
question, why didn't we say it was the cracked grapes? And the
answer is that יין נסך Yayin Nesech, when it's מין במינו, min
be'mino, it's wine with wine or maybe wine with grapes or the...
I understand. We'll get to wine with grapes. Then it's אסור assur
even בכל שהוא. be'chol she'hu. That's not normal הלכה, the normal טריפה
treifa issues, but it's true by יין yayin that מין במינו min
be'mino is בכל שהוא. be'chol she'hu. But אינו מינו, eino mino, and
this becomes the general principle of course in כשרות, Kashrut, if it's
mixed up with something that's not of its kind, then it goes
by the ability... is there enough that it's tasteable? נותן טעם. Nosein
ta'am. And that's one of the most basic principles of טהרה Tahara
or... So this was like real wine. Because let's say it would
have been like ערק Arrak mixed with figs, then would it be
נותן טעם? nosein ta'am? Yeah, but ערק Arrak is not יין נסך,
Yayin Nesech ערק Arrak is liquor. No but saying if they would
have used whatever... anyway, yeah, okay. נפל על גבי תאנים או על
גבי תמרים אם יש בהן בנותן טעם, Nafal al gabei te'einim o
al gabei temarim im yesh bahen benosein ta'am, if it's enough to
be tasted אסור, assur, it's forbidden. ומעשה בביתוס בן זונם, U'ma'aseh be'Veitos
ben Zonam, story with the Beitos ben Zonam who was somewhat of
a businessman, שהביא גרוגרות בספינה, she'heivi grugros bisfina, he brought these dried
figs in the in a ship, ונשתבר חבית של יין נסך, venishtaber
chavis shel yayin nesech, and a barrel of יין נסך Yayin Nesech.
broke. Now what was he doing? Maybe it wasn't his ship, some
other person was transporting יין נסך. yayin nesech Anyway, ונפל עליהן, venafal
aleihen, and the... and it fell onto these figs. ושאל חכמים, Vesha'al
chachamim, and he asked the sages what's the story, והתירום, vehitirum, and
they permitted it. זה הכלל, Ze ha'klal, this... why? Was it so
little that it wasn't tasteable? So it sounds like no, there might
have been another principle at work which is the next line. Not
just it has to be enough to be tasted, but it has
to be a good taste. This is the rule. כל שבנאתו בנותן
טעם, Kol she'be'hana'ato benosein ta'am, anything with the taste is... it's a
funny grammar here. Anything which in its pleasure is taste. But really
means within its taste is pleasure. Anything that gives taste and it's
a pleasurable taste, a positive taste, אסור, assur, it's forbidden. וכל שאין
בהנאתו בנותן טעם מותר. Vechol she'ein be'hana'ato benosein ta'am mutar. But if
it's not a positive... so it has two things. It has to
be able to be tasted and it has to be a good
taste. Is that subjective? Let's say I hate wine and to me
that's bad, but you like it and for you it's good. It
doesn't seem that it's subjective, but it does seem that it is
case by case in the sense of like we don't have some
big principles like whatever. The simple answer would be no, it's not
totally subjective. Okay, but it's a good question. כגון חומץ שנפל על
גבי גריסין. Kegon chometz she'nafal al gabei grisin. An example would be
vinegar that fell on like a type of oatmeal or whatever, that
would be a bad taste, that would be not good. But Michael
is... does a good question. Is it subjective or not? It doesn't
seem like there's some abstract rules. Like you know, like you don't
have a rule wine and fig, whatever you know, wine and figs
is always good or it's always bad. Like it might depend, what's
the wine? What's the fig? You know, what's the taste of the
people in the locale? But it's not like, but the question about
could it be מותר muttar for me and אסור assur for Michael,
that's already a different level of question. But let's take a look
at the גמרא. Gemara. מעשה לסתור? Maise listor? Your story contradicts your
rule because your story says if it's tasteable and then it's a
problem, and your story said it was okay, and presumably wine on
figs is a good taste. So the גמרא Gemara says no, חסורי
מחסרא והכי קתני, chisore mechsara v'hachi katani, I'm sorry, not good taste.
Presumably wine on figs, it's not clear from the story that it
wasn't tasteable, presumably the story sounds like even though it was tasteable,
it was okay. חסורי מחסרא והכי קתני. chisore mechsara v'hachi katani. You're
right. We should have introduced before the story the principle that the
משנה Mishnah ends with. The bad taste principle. ונותן טעם לפגם מותר.
noten ta'am lifgam muttar. So not only if it's tasteable is it
a problem, but is it always a problem? If it's a bad
taste, then even if you can taste it, it's okay. And that's
what the story is an illustration of. ומעשה נמי ביוסי בן זונין
שהיה מביא גרוגרות בספינה ונשתברה חבית של יין נסך ונפל עליהן ובא
מעשה לפני חכמים וטהרום. u'maise nami be-Yosei ben Zohnim shehayah meivi grogerot
bi-sefinah ve-nishtaber ha-chavit shel yayin nesech ve-nafal gabeihen u-va maaseh lifnei chachamim
ve-tiherum. Okay, they permitted it. I could have understood that without the
חסורי מחסרא. chisore mechsara. Yeah, but the problem is that you want
to introduce the rule before the illustration. As opposed to the way
the משנה Mishnah is, here's the rule, if you can taste it,
it's a problem. Oh, by the way, here was a case where
they could taste it and it was okay. Why? Because of the
following rule. So instead of saying, you know, you should have introduced
the rule before the illustration. Okay, ההוא כרי דחיטי. hahu kariy d'chiti.
Now, there was a pile of wheat דנפל עליה חבית דיין נסך
d'nafal alei chavis d'yayin nesech that a barrel of יין נסך presumably
broke and spilled on it. שריה רבא לזבוני לעובדי כוכבים. sharya Rava
lizvonei l'ovdei kochavim. He permitted to sell it to a non-Jew. איתיביה
רבה בר ליואי לרבא. eisevei Rabbah bar Liva'i l'Rava. He said, why
now are you allowed to do that? Meaning, presumably he was saying,
okay, it's אסור בהנאה, assur behana'ah, but I'm, you know, are you
selling it to a non-Jew חוץ דמי היין שבו? chutz d'mei ha-yayin
shebo? So presumably, like you know, if it's now worth more because
of the wine, presumably you can't charge the extra, you're getting הנאה
hana'ah from the wine. Okay, but he, רבא, basically said it's אסור
assur to drink, eat, sell it, and don't get benefit from the
wine. Okay, now we got a question. Why are you allowed to
sell it? And forget the getting benefit from the wine. The non-Jew
is going to turn around and sell the wheat to a Jew.
Okay, so you might not be getting any money off of the
wine, but it's a danger for other application Jews. בגד שעבד בו
כלאים הרי זה לא ימכרנו לעובד כוכבים, beged she-avad bo kilayim harei
zeh lo yimkarenu l'oved kochavim, don't sell it to a non-Jew and
don't make it like a saddle blanket for a donkey. Saddle blanket
for a donkey is that maybe it'll like turn up and be
on top of you and it'll be like you're wearing כלאים. kilayim.
אבל עושה תכריכין למת מצוה, aval oseh tachrichin l'meis mitzvah, but you
can make it for shrouds for a dead because they're not obligated
in the מצוות. mitzvot. כלאים אסור במשהו? kilayim assur bil-ma-she-hu? No. But
that's not the reason. Let's keep on reading. Okay, so anyway, you
can use it for shrouds for the dead because it's not אסור
בהנאה assur behana'ah and the dead isn't commanded. So the גמרא Gemara
says לעובד כוכבים מאי טעמא לא? l'oved kochavim mai ta'ama lo? But
why can't you sell it to a non-Jew? So it says דילמא
אתי לזבוני לישראל, dilma ati lizvonei l'Yisrael, because he'll turn around and
sell it to a Jew. הכא נמי אתי לזבוני לישראל, hacha nami
ati lizvonei l'Yisrael, so here too, I get that it's not הנאה,
hana'ah, but why aren't you afraid he'll turn around and sell it
to a Jew? So הדר שריה? hadar sharya? It said, you're right,
you're right, I made a mistake. So הדר שריה למטחניה, hadar sharya
l'midchino, presumably it hadn't been sold yet to the Jew, to a
non-Jew, so he said, fine, don't sell it to a non-Jew, here's
what you can do though. Grind it up, למיפיינו ולזביניהו לעובדי כוכבים
l'mifyeinu v'lizvineihu l'ovdei kochavim and sell it as bread to a non-Jew.
שלא בפני ישראל, shelo bifnei Yisrael, not in the presence of Yisrael.
Why? Because then nobody would buy bread from the non-Jew going back
to the principle of the problem about פת עכו"ם, pat akum, assuming
it's not פת פלטר pas palter or they're not going with the
היתר heter of פת פלטר. pas palter. So they won't buy it
from him because it'll be bread and they won't buy it because
they'll know it's bread of a non-Jew. But that's why you can't
do it in front of other Jews. Because if a Jew sees
you selling the bread, they'll think, oh, it's bread of a Jew,
I can buy it from him. So fine, you have to take
steps to make sure he won't turn around and sell it to
Jews. So now I understand your question, Michael. Yes, there is discussions
in the משניות Mishnayot about how much of כלאים kilayim is a
problem. Okay, but it's a little bit different what עבד בו avad
bo and does it go by normal laws of תערובת. ta'aruvet. Like
if you know that there's a little, a little area stitched in
and you can't find, anyway, it's a good question which I'm not
going to get into, about how do you deal with תערובת ta'aruvet
by כלאים. kilayim. Okay, so anyway, let's just do one more line.
תנן, tenan, יין נסך שנפל על גבי ענבים ידיחם. yayin nesech she-nafal
al gabei anavim yadi-chem. Back to our משנה, Mishnah, rinse off the
grapes. והן מותרות. ve-hen mutarot. ואם היו מבוקעות אסורות, ve-im hayu mevukaot
assura, but if they're cracked grapes, it's a problem. מבוקעות אין שאין
מבוקעות לא. mevukaot in, she-ein mevukaot lo. So the גמרא Gemara says,
so I don't get why your grain, your wheat was a problem.
The wheat wasn't cracked, so why not just rinse it off? Why
do we assume it got absorbed into the wheat kernels? So the
גמרא Gemara says אמר רב פפא שאני חיטי הוא ואגב צירייהו כמבוקעות
דמי amar Rav Papa shani chiti ho ve-agav tzira-yu k'mevukaos dami because
wheat has, it does have a nick in it, right? Like a
wheat kernel has sort of like a nick. So it might not
actually be cracked. Anyway, whatever it does, it has like a groove
in it. So that groove, we assume, will still be a way
in which the wine can get in. Okay? It's sort of like,
you know, the more porous nature of like the dates as opposed
to the grapes. So yes, we are afraid that even in cold,
the wine will get into the wheat; it won't get into the
grape. And that's why it was a problem, and it was presumably
נותן טעם לשבח; noten ta'am leshevach; it wasn't נותן טעם לפגם. noten
ta'am lifgam. So sell it, sell it in a way that it
won't get turned around and sold to another Jew. Alright.